Mazal Tov, today's דף daf *daf* is קייט *Kuf Yud Tet* 119
and the last דף daf *daf* of בבא קמא *Bava Kama*. Let's
get going. We pick up with a bottom of ק''ח עמוד ב
*Kuf Yud Chet amud bet*, the two dots. רבי יהודה אומר *Rabbi
Yehuda omer* ביתות לוקחין מהן מדבריות אין לוקחין מהן *beisos lokhin mehen
midbarios ein lokhin mehen*. This is about purchasing things from shepherds because
you have to be concerned that they are stolen. So can you
buy sheep? Can you buy milk? Can you buy wool? And
רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* says if they're home animals, I guess kept
close to town, then you're allowed to do it because the owner
will notice that they're gone. One or two it's a problem because
they might be stealing it from the owner and they'll get away
with it. Okay, so רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* says if they're home
animals,
ביתות *beisos*,
then you can buy because the owner will immediately realize it. But
if they're animals that are just raised out in the wilderness, מדבריות
*midbarios*, אין לוקחין מהן *ein lokhin mehen*, you can't buy, the owner
won't know they're gone. So איבעיא להו Ibaiya lehu, *ibay-u lehu*, there
is the question. רבי יהודה רישא קאי לחומרא או דלמא סיפא קאי
לקולא *Rabbi Yehuda reisha kaei lechumra o dilma seifa kaei lekula*. Is
he going on the first part that you're allowed to buy like
four or five animals, and he's being strict? You need two criteria:
both be a lot of animals and they be home animals. Or
is he going on the end? You're not allowed to buy two
or three and he's being lenient, that you're not allowed to buy
two or three unless they're home animals and then you are. Okay,
is it both criteria are needed or either criteria is needed? רישא
קאי לחומרא דאמר לוקחין ארבע וחמש *reisha kaei lechumra d-amar lokhin arba
ve-chamesh*, you can buy four or five sheep from a shepherd, צאן
הני מילי ביתות *tzon hani milei beisos*, only if that's with an
additional criterion that they are home animals. אבל מדבריות *aval midbarios*, but
if animals that are generally kept out in the wilderness, אפילו ארבע
וחמש לא *afilu arba ve-chamesh lo*, even four and five you can't,
you need both criteria in order to buy it. או דלמא *o
dilma*, or סיפא קאי לקולא דאמר אבל לא שתי sheti צאן ולא
שתי sheti גיזין *seifa kaei lekula d-amar aval lo shtei tzon ve-lo
shtei gizin*, you cannot buy two sheep or two bunches of wool,
הני מילי מדבריות *hani milei midbarios*, that's only if they're kept out
in the wilderness. אבל ביתות *aval beisos*, but if they're kept at
home, שתים נמי לוקחין *shtayim nami lokhin*, you can even buy two.
Okay, so it's either that you buy a lot or they're animals
that are at home. תא שמע Ta shema, *ta shema*, come and
hear, מהך דתניא detanya, *me-hakh de-tanya*, it was taught in a ברייתא
Braisa *braita*. רבי יהודה אומר לוקחין ביתות מהן ואין לוקחין מדבריות מהן
*Rabbi Yehuda omer lokhin beisos mehen ve-ein lokhin midbarios mehen*, you can
buy home animals from them and not the animals from the wilderness,
ובכל מקום לוקחין מהן ארבע וחמש צאן *u-ve-khol makom lokhin mehen arba
ve-chamesh tzon*. And anywhere you are you can buy four or five.
So that makes it very clear: it's one or the other. Either
a large number or a small number with home animals.
מדאמר בכל מקום *mid-amar be-khol makom*, since he says "anywhere you are",
שמע מינא סיפא קאי *shma mina seifa kaei*, he's going on the
end, ולכולא שמע מינא *u-lekula shma mina*, and he's being lenient. Either
criterion is enough. Okay. Good. ולא משומרי פירות *ve-lo mi-shomrei peiros*, you
cannot buy from people that watch fruit, you can't buy עצים ופירות
*etzin u-peiros*, wood and fruit, okay, because that's not, you're afraid where
did they get the wood and fruit to sell, presumably they took
it from the garden they were supposed to be watching. Okay. רב
זבין שבישתא מאריסא *Rav zavin shavishata me-arisa*, Rav purchased a bundle of
wood from a sharecropper. אמר ליה אביי *amar lei Abaye*, Abaye said
to him, והא תנן לא משומרי פירות עצים ופירות *ve-ha tnan lo
mi-shomrei peiros etzin u-peiros*, you can't buy from people who watch fruit,
you cannot buy from them wood and fruit.
Or is an אריסא *arisa* someone who actually owns this?
That's the answer. The question was what was even the question. אמר
ליה הני מילי בשומר *amar lei hani milei be-shomer*, that's a normal,
you know, watcher, a paid watchman, דלית ליה בגופא דארעא מידי *de-leise
lei begufa de-ara midei*, that he doesn't get a portion in the
grain, in the produce, he just gets a fee, he just gets
a straight paycheck. Okay. אבל אריס aris דאית ליה בגופא *aval aris
de-is lei begufa*, but a sharecropper that gets a portion of the
actual produce, אימר מידי דנפשיה קמזבין *aimar midei de-nafshei ka-mazbin*, he's selling
his own produce, he's not necessarily
selling the owner's produce. So therefore that's a reasonable assumption and you
can buy it. תנו רבנן Tanu rabanan, *tana rabanan*, I have no
idea. תנו רבנן tanu rabanan. *tana rabanan*, שומרי פירות לוקחין מהן כשהן
יושבין ומוכרין והסלין לפניהן *shomrei peiros lokhin mehen ke-she-hen yoshvin u-mokhrin ve-ha-salin
le-fanehen*. Here's another way you can buy from them: if they are
obviously doing it in such a blatant public out-in-the-open way that they
must have been with the owner's, you know, knowledge. Okay. So there
they are, they've got a big fruit stand by the edge of
the road, right, fresh produce here, you know what do they call
it,
farm stand or whatever, right, and they're doing it in total public,
so nobody, so clearly the owner would have to be aware of
it. All right. What? Well that's an interesting question, like right, let's
say this is like 20 miles out of town and you know,
but still the assumption seems to be that if it's so public
the word would get to the owner. They would not be that
brazen. Okay. שומרי פירות לוקחין מהן כשהן יושבין ומוכרין *shomrei peiros lokhin
mehen ke-she-hen yoshvin u-mokhrin*, they're sitting and they're selling, it's not just
like somebody, you know, bumps into you in an alley. They got
a stand set up. Okay, והסלין לפניהן *ve-ha-salin le-fanehen*, the baskets of
fruit are in front of
them, והתורתני לפניהן *ve-ha-turtani le-fanehen*, they've got these big scales in front
of them. That's okay. וכולן שאמרו הטמן *ve-khulan she-amru hatmen*, but whatever
the circumstances are, if the guy says keep it to yourself, then
אסור assur *assur*, then it's forbidden. Okay. Now, לוקחין מהן מפתח הגינה
אבל לא מאחורי הגינה *lokhin mehen
mi-petach ha-gina aval lo me-achorei ha-gina*. Now again, it's not clear to
me whether you need these other conditions as well, right, you can
buy from them... If they are at the front of the garden,
but not, you know, not in the back alley, not in the
back entrance. Now, does that mean the front of the garden you
can even buy like a like you know a little bundle of
fruit without this whole setup? Right? So you know it's like it's
not clear like what the various collection of circumstances are. It sounds
like that's sufficient.
אבל לא מאחורי הגינה. איתמר itmar was taught: גזלן מאימתי מותר לקנות
הימנו? gazlan me'ematai mutar liknot himenu? This guy is a גזלן, gazlan,
sort of like before you know we had the, what do you
call it, if you remember we had the tax collector, and you
could change money if you're doing it, you know, with in his
house or money he's got in his normal wallet, but not from
the basket, you know, not from the money funds that the, the
box that he puts all the tax funds. So here's a similar
question. Some guy is known to be a גזלן. gazlan. When can
you buy things from him? You don't know this object is stolen.
You know, he does have his own stuff. Do you have to
always be חושש choshesh that he's selling you stolen goods? Now I
assume that it has something to do with what types of things
is he selling you, you know, is he selling you a used
potato peeler? Probably okay. If he's selling you a VCR brand new
in the box, probably not okay. You know, sell off a truck
somewhere. Okay. So anyway, let's see what the גמרא gemara says. Okay.
I know, not VCR, okay, the iPhone, new in the box. Okay.
איתמר גזלן מאימתי מותר לקנות ממנו. itmar gazlan me'ematai mutar liknot mimenu.
When are you allowed? I gotta give equal billing to Samsung. מאימתי
מותר לקנות ממנו. me'ematai mutar liknot mimenu. When can you buy from
him? רב אמר עד כדי רוב משלו. rav amar ad kedei rov
mishelo. Until the majority of, now what is that? The majority of
things that he owns, the majority of things that he sells? It
sounds like just the majority of things that he owns. Does רש״י
rashi say? I don't know if רש״י rashi even says. What?
רש״י rashi says, רוב ממונו משלו ולא גזילה. rov mamono mishelo velo
gezeilah. Okay,
as long as most of his property, okay, I don't even know
how you measure that, right? Let's say the land and the house,
which is
obviously 70% of his net worth, that's his, but all of the
objects in the house are stolen. You know, exactly how you measure.
Anyway, but Rav says it has to be more likely than not
that he's selling you his own object, that's the way I'd explain
it. עד כדי רוב משלו. ad kedei rov mishelo.
By that logic, you could have done business with Bernie Madoff.
What, most of his property was his own?
No, most of his operation was actually legit.
Oh, really? שמואל אמר אפילו מיעוט שלו. shmuel amar afilu miyut shelo.
Even if only a minority. Okay, which is interesting, right? Because now
the question is I guess the question partly here is like what
איסור issur are you doing? And the thing that is absent from
this entire גמרא, gemara, and it's really, it came up like once
many דף Daf. ago and it comes up in other גמרות, gemarot,
is the problem of providing a market for stolen goods, because you
know the גמרא gemara sort of says, the גמרא gemara has a
saying like, it's not the rat that steals, it's the hole that
steals, you know, because you know if you don't provide a market,
then you know you are really making this an enterprise. So here
the גמרא gemara seems to be unconcerned with that, right? As long
as like we saw before and we're going to see again, as
long as the object underwent a שינוי shinui and technically it's not
stolen goods, you can buy it. And there's like this there is
absent from this discussion a concern of providing a market for the
guy. Okay. But whatever, so but the problem still is like what?
Like you don't want to be taking an object that belongs to
somebody else. You'll also be stealing an object if it belongs to
somebody else. So why is it that you can even a מיעוט
miyut is enough? If it's going against the חזקה chazaka of חזקה
מה שתחת יד אדם הרי הוא שלו? chazaka ma shetachat yad adam
harei hu shelo? Even when you know in fact that the majority
of his stuff or you assume is stolen. You know, in other
cases for example, the thing that this makes me think of is
if I allowed to lend you an object if I, if if
there's more likely than not that you're going to use it to
do an איסור. issur. Like for example it's שמיטה shmita and you
are known to work your field on שמיטה shmita and you ask
me to borrow a hose or something. Can I lend it to
you? Because more likely than not you're going to use it to
do an איסור issur on שמיטה. shmita. No, maybe you're just going
to use your hose to, I don't know, fill up
your swimming pool in the backyard. So actually there we tend to
פוסקן pasken in terms of that לפני עיוור lifnei iver question that
as long as it's like a reasonable possibility, you know, even if
it's a minority possibility, it's a but it's even a small possibility
you'll use it for היתר, heter, it's not לפני עיוור. lifnei iver.
Okay. But that's like a different thing. That's like is it am
I abetting your sin, what are you going to use this for
in the future, how much do I have to anticipate and am
I seen as abetting is like a different חשבון cheshbon than am
I taking possession of stolen goods? And if I and if the
majority of the goods are stolen, it's not clear to me why
I'm allowed to rely on the minority possibility you know that they're
not, unless it's like חזקה מה שתחת יד אדם הרי הוא שלו.
chazaka ma shetachat yad adam harei hu shelo. You know, the חזקה
chazaka that what you're holding on is yours counters the majority reality
that most of your goods are stolen. I really don't understand the
logic here, okay, but interestingly it's going to seem that that's how
we are how we פוסקן. pasken. שמואל אמר אפילו מיעוט שלו, shmuel
amar afilu miyut shelo, even if a minority.
And what about the stuff over here like the רועה? ro'eh?
Right, I mean, so then the question is that there the point
is that all the property isn't his. All those sheep aren't his.
Does he ever own sheep ever?
Yes, I don't know exactly, you know, and I don't know, that's
a case where maybe other circumstances, right? How much does this discussion
of רוב... rov... how much does this discussion of רוב rov and
מיעוט mi'ut deal with like other circumstantial evidence of what's going on?
Right. So like that whole חשבון cheshbon is absent. Alright? Right. שמואל
Shmuel
if your question is can שמואל Shmuel be abstracted to not the
question of the majority of your property is yours or it's stolen,
but the question of it's 95% likely that you're selling me stolen
goods but 5% likely that you're not. Right. Can you abstract that
to just that question of how likely is it as opposed to
what is the quantity of stolen goods that you have? I don't
know the answer to that.
I mean if you want to מדייק medayek then harmonize with our
משנה mishnah with the רועה ro'eh and the whoever else it is,
and the שומר, shomer, you know, then it would be it's only
the רועה ro'eh is only רועה ro'eh of בהמות, behemot, but if
he puts his own animals in there too.
Right, which is sort of my the question maybe about the אריס
aris a little bit the question of the אריס before. So if
yeah, it's hard to know how to abstract and generalize this and
it's a real hard to know what the guiding principle here is.
Okay, שמואל אמר אפילו מיעוטו שלו Shmuel amar afilu mi'uto shelo
even if of only a minority is his. Because by the way,
I should say right also the shepherd, you don't know he's a
גזלן. gazlan. So by the shepherd you could say even if it's
10% likely, maybe I should assume the best of people, right, and
I should assume 10% likely he's from his own sheep, why shouldn't
I assume that he's doing that that he's an honest guy. Here
you know the guy's a גזלן. gazlan. You know 70% of the
goods in his home are stolen goods, right? It seems very strange
that you're allowed even מיעוטו שלו mi'uto shelo you can buy from
him. What?
You know that he also had some property.
I understand, but you know the majority are stolen and he's a
גזלן. gazlan. I find it hard to understand. Okay. And you may
be keeping him in business. Okay, so אוביליה רב יהודה לאדא דיילא
oveilei Rav Yehuda le-Ada Dayala so רב יהודה Rav Yehuda taught אדא
Ada who was his attendant, a rabbinic
attendant, כדידי אמר אפילו מיעוטו שלו kedidi amar afilu mi'uto shelo even
as long as the minority is his you can buy from a
גזלן. gazlan. Okay, fascinating. Now, a different question which I don't know
why it's related here, should have gone on the previous סוגיא, sugya,
ממון מסור, mamon masur, the money of a person who is an
informer. Now, you normally assume the word informer means he informs of
the government and hands somebody over to the government, which is he's
endangering somebody's life. רש"י Rashi points us to a discussion of in
עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah that which might remind you of the רב
כהנא Rav Kahana story, that even if he's just handing property of
somebody over to the government, that is he's considered a רודף rodef
because when you hand property of somebody that gets the government's claws
into that person and eventually could endanger that person's life. So even
somebody who's just מוסר ממון חבירו moser mamon chaveiro is considered as
a רודף. rodef. Okay, so he says this case of מסור masur
is even just handing over property of somebody else to the government.
So that person, ראובן Reuven is handing over שמעון's Shimon property to
the government, what's the story with ראובן's Reuven property? רב הונא ורב
יהודה, Rav Huna ve-Rav Yehuda, חד אמר מותר לאבדו ביד. chad amar
mutar le-abdo be-yad. You can just willfully destroy ראובן's Reuven property, right,
presumably as some type of a punishment even if you're not going
to kill ראובן Reuven in the act.
Even before he feels the torture.
Yeah, exactly, you could torture his fields, some type of societal, you
know, way of controlling this. You understand this, right? You had to
keep away from the government and right, it endangered the Jewish community,
so if we're allowed to, you know, kill ראובן Reuven as the
גמרא Gemara in עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah says, you know, because of
that, so we can go ahead and torture his property. וחד אמר
אסור לאבדו, ve-chad amar assur le-abdo, no you're not allowed. מאן דאמר
מותר לאבדו ביד, man de-amar mutar le-abdo be-yad, לא יהא ממונו חמור
מגופו, lo yehei mamono chamur mi-gufo, if his money should not be
more valuable than his person. So if you can actually, you know,
kill him in order to stop him, you can torture his property.
Now, of course, the different argument could be, you could kill him
in the process when he's, you know, to stop him from doing
it, like the רודף rodef who's in the act. You know, this
is like an after the fact punishment, it's not exactly the same
as stopping a person in the act. Okay, maybe or maybe it's
a before the fact punishment, I don't know. ומאן דאמר אסור לאבדו,
u-man de-amar assur le-abdo, no you can't destroy his property, דילמא הוי
ליה זרעא מעליא, dilma havei lei zara me-alya, no because even though
you the property will be go down to his kids, and even
though you can stop him and he deserves to be, you know,
stopped and maybe punished, but it's not fair to the kids. Maybe
he'll have kids that are that are good kids and not as
רשעים resha'im like him. דכתיב יכין רשע וצדיק ילבש, dichshiv yachin rasha
ve-tzaddik yilbash, the righteous the wicked man will prepare and the righteous
one will wear it. So you know, he's amassing all of this
wealth and again maybe part of the issue is that maybe he
gets paid for this service to the government, okay maybe that is
part of it. Anyway, so the kids at least why should you
destroy the property? You know, let at least, you know, his kids
get it. Which is interesting because still even if that's a, you
know, a concern, it's also not fair that the kids don't have
a father. You know, you have to do stuff in order to
protect the interests of the community if this was really seen as
endangering the community.
Remember that issue of כיבוד אב, kibbud av, when we
had yeah, that was about right, that was about the kids returning
stolen objects. Right. Okay. Anyway, this is about this is a little
bit of a digression going back to yesterday's discussion. רב חסדא הוה
ליה ההוא אריסא Rav Chisda hava lei hahu arisa back to well
we'll see what this is. Sharecropper, again it's not this is no
longer this is now actually continuing to some degree with the digression.
It's no longer a question about whether you assume it's stolen goods
or not but about what we'll see, about
let's read it. רב חסדא הוה ליה ההוא אריסא, Rav Chisda hava
lei hahu arisa, he had a sharecropper, הוה תקיל ויהיב תקיל ושקיל.
hava takeil ve-yahiv takeil ve-shakil. He would weigh and give, weigh and
take. So what's the matter with that? So רש"י Rashi says it
means well maybe he means that he would be overly precise in
the division. He wouldn't sort of just like, you know, it was
no big deal. People are entitled to be precise and make sure
they're getting exactly what's coming to them. So the other explanation רש"י
Rashi has is he would divide it fifty-fifty and normal sharecroppers get
only like a quarter or a third. But still, if that's the
deal that רב חסדא Rav Chisda made, big deal. Okay, you made
the deal, live with it. So the מהרש"א Maharsha has the better
explanation I think. The מהרש"א Maharsha says it means that he would
he would take with one set of measures and he'd give with
another set of measures, meaning it's the אבן ואבן, even v'even, right?
So when I weigh out my ten pounds, I'm using one set
of weights. When I weigh out the ten pounds you the owner
gets, I use a different set of weights. Okay, so anyway he
was cheating רב חסדא. Rav Chisda. Okay. סלקיה, salkei, so רב חסדא
Rav Chisda basically removed him. He fired him. Okay. קרא אנפשיה, k'ra
anafshei, so רב חסדא Rav Chisda said about himself,
and treasured away for the righteous person is the wealth of the
sinner. So it's interesting, he fired him and what, he took his
portion? I mean maybe I don't know maybe that was a clause
in the contract that if you know, that you forfeit your whatever.
But anyway, it's a similar it sort of echoes both points before.
Number one is he was stealing from the owner. And number two
is, you know, the wealth of the of the wicked can go
to somebody who deserves it. All right. Now the גמרא Gemara says
like this: כי מה תקות חנף כי יבצע כי ישל
אלוה נפשו. ki mah tikvat chanef ki yivatza ki yeshal Eloka nafsho.
Now we're going to look at a different פסוק. pasuk. What benefit
is it? Now fascinating, it took us 118 דף to finally get
to the to the, you know, issue of transgression.
Like the entire מסכת masechet with all about the consequences of the
sort of
financial consequences of theft and מזיק mazik and חובל chovel and all
of that. Almost completely absent was the issue about about like how
אסור it is and how bad it is what the person is
doing. And sometimes it was it was really a problem because it
talked about, you know, תקנת השבים, takanat hashavim, תקנת takanat you know,
and and the גנב ganav doesn't have to pay for this and
he at least can keep the usage and all these types of
things which really bothered us. Finally now at the end, the גמרא
Gemara is turning to the question about how terrible this act of
theft is. So let's take a look. כי מה תקות חנף, ki
mah tikvat chanef, what good is it for the flatterer or, you
know,
how do they translate the word חנף? chanef? Hypocrite. Okay. If he
if he steals כי יבצע ki yivatza like to take money that
is not his, כי ישל אלוה נפשו, ki yeshal Eloka nafsho, the
Lord will remove his soul. So רב הונא Rav Huna ורב חסדא.
v'Rav Chisda. חד אמר chad amar נפשו של נגזל, nafsho shel nignzal,
it means the soul of the person he is stealing from, which
means you think you're just stealing this person's wealth, but you are
not you are not appreciating the enormity of your action. You're taking
of his wealth really is a type of a murder. Of course
why turns to God? God will take his soul. But okay, it
means you know he'll die, you know, so you effectively can cause
his him to be taken an act of taking his life. וחד
אמר v'chad amar נפשו של גזלן. nafsho shel gazlan. No, it means
God will punish, will kill the גזלן. gazlan. Okay, either way it's
talking about the enormity of the sin. מאן דאמר man d'amar נפשו
של נגזל nafsho shel nignzal דכתיב, dich'tiv, כן ארחות כל בצע בצע
את נפש בעליו יקח, ken orchot kol botzea batza et nefesh ba'alav
yikach, these are the ways of all who take ill-gotten
gains, they take the soul of the owner of the property. They
think they're just taking property but they're actually taking the person's life.
מאן דאמר man d'amar נפשו של גזלן, nafsho shel gazlan, no, God
will take the soul of the גזלן gazlan דכתיב, dich'tiv, אל תגזול
דל כי דל הוא, al tizgol dal ki dal hu, do not
steal from the poor person you think ah he's a poor person
you can get away from him away with it, ואל תדכא עני
בשער, v'al t'dakeh ani basha'ar, do not trample down on the on
the on the poor person in the gate, כי ה' יריב ריבם,
ki Hashem yariv rivam, for God will come and defend and fight
their fight וקבע את קבעיהם נפש, v'kava et koveihem nafesh, and will
steal from their stealers a soul, meaning so you stole from them
God will take away your soul. Okay. ואידך נמי v'idach nami הא
כתיב hach'tiv נפש בעליו יקח? nefesh ba'alav yikach? Now the one that
says it's the soul of the גזלן, gazlan, what does he do
with this other פסוק pasuk that says that when you take you
take
their soul, the soul of the owner which seems to be the
נגזל, nignzal, the one who is stolen from? No, מאי בעליו בעליו
דהשתא. mai ba'alav ba'alav d'hashta. No, no. It means God will take
the soul of the current owner, again of the גזלן. gazlan. So
the גזלן gazlan will be punished as a result.
ואידך נמי v'idach
nami הא כתיב hach'tiv וקבע את קבעיהם נפש? v'kava et koveihem nafesh?
That it says that if you say it focuses on it's like
taking the soul of the נגזל, nignzal, what about the verse that
says that God will steal the their soul of the גזלן? gazlan?
Of course you could say both are true. Some פסוקים psukim talk
about killing the נגזל nignzal other פסוקים psukim talk about the גזלן
gazlan being deserving of death. But no,
the גמרא Gemara says: מה טעם קאמר, ma ta'am ka'amar, מה טעם
וקבע את קבעיהם, ma ta'am v'koveh et koveihem, why will God take
the soul you know murder not murder but whatever execute the the
גזלן, gazlan, take the soul of the גזלן, gazlan, משום דקבעי נפש,
mishum d'kava'ei nefesh, because the גזלן gazlan took the soul of the
נגזל. nignzal. Both are true. It's like murdering the נגזל nignzal and
therefore you're deserving of death. Okay, so finally we get this like,
you know, the
the exhortations about it are finally coming at the way end of
the מסכת masechet and, you know, and really talking about the enormity
of it. It's like you actually murdered, especially a poor person they
can't put food on the table. Okay, how tragic that is.
What's the fourth set of word
No, I don't know, I don't think it's from the word קבע.
Keva. You have to ask the biblical grammarians, but it seems more
to be like to seize, to steal, to take. Okay, אמר רבי
יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan, כל הגוזל חברו שוה פרוטה כאילו נוטל ננשמתו.
Kol hagozel chavero shaveh prutah ke'ilu notel nishmato. So now just saying
it as a straight statement, not a different דרוש Drush of a
פסוק, Pasuk, and really emphasizing even if it's just a dollar, actually
a פרוטה Prutah is more like a penny,
even if you just take a penny, it's like you took their
soul.
שנאמר, Shene'emar, כן ארחות כל בצע בצע את נפש בעליו יקח, Ken
orchot kol botzea batza et nefesh be'alav yikach, reading the פסוק Pasuk
like one of the readings before, its simple sense to the פסוק,
Pasuk, it is like taking their soul. Okay, ואומר Ve'omer and it
says, ואכל קצירך ולחמך, Ve'achal katzircha velachmecha, you, they will eat, he,
the you
know, the גנב, Gannav, will eat your bread and your harvest, יאכלו
בניך ובנותיך, Yochlu banecha uvnotocha, it will be like יאכלו בניך ובנותיך
Yochlu banecha uvnotocha is really is the... it will be like they
are destroying, killing your children.
ואומר Ve'omer the verse says, now of course the simple sense is
that if you need the money and you're poor and you can't
put food on the table and so on, but I think also
there's a sense here of you know, a particularly of like that
of violation, right? Particularly in a case of גניבה, Gneivah, but it's
true I mean even in גזילה Gzeilah as well. In גניבה Gneivah
they talk about that sense of losing their sense of security in
your own home with the one place you thought you were protected,
right? And now it's being sort of you know violated, so there's
that so I think that's also a piece of it. ואומר Ve'omer
and it also says, מחמת בני יהודה אשר שפכו דם נקי בארצם,
Mechamas benei Yehudah asher shafchu dam naki be'artzam, from the חמס. Chamas.
Now חמס Chamas is understood rabbinically to mean taking something and paying
the owner but forcing the owner to sell when the owner didn't
want to sell. Okay, so because of the חמס Chamas of the
sons of Yehudah, they have spilled you know innocent blood, so just
even thank you so much, just just like taking it, thank you,
okay, just the act of חמס Chamas is like spilling blood. ואומר
Ve'omer and it says,
אל שאול ואל בית הדמים אשר המית את הגבעונים, El Shaul ve'el
beit hadamim asher hemit et haGivonim, he killed the גבעונים. Givonim. And
the גמרא Gemara is going to say he didn't actually directly kill
the גבעונים, Givonim, what he did was he prevented them from earning
a livelihood. Okay, so מאי ואומר? Mai Ve'omer? Why do you need
all four פסוקים? Psukim? וכי תימא, Vechi teima, because you're going to
say נפש דידיה, Nefesh didei, yes, it's like you took the soul
of the person you stole from, אבל נפש בניו ובנותיו לא, Aval
nefesh banav uvnotav lo, but it's not as bad as actually killing
their children, תא שמע, Ta shema, בשר בניו ובנותיו, Besar banav uvnotav,
no,
it says it's like you took the flesh of their children, you
killed their children, you prevented them from being from getting you know
fed. וכי תימא, Vechi teima, הני מילי היכא דלא יהיב דמי, Hani
milei heicha d'lo yahiv damei, that's only if you steal without reimbursement.
אבל היכא דיהיב דמי, Aval heicha dyahiv damei, if you steal and
you reimburse, so at least the guy has money to put food
on the table, he might have lost his object, so maybe that's
not so bad, it's not like you... it's bad but it's not
like you killed him. תא שמע, Ta shema, מחמת בני יהודה, Mechamas
benei Yehudah, חמס Chamas meaning here understood to mean taking and forcing
a guy to sell, אשר שפכו דם נקי בארצם, Asher shafchu dam
naki be'artzam, they spilled innocent blood. Okay, so again there really it's
not like just the guy doesn't have money to put food on
the table, it really is that sense of you know violation, being
stripped of things that are part of you and so on. וכי
תימא, Vechi teima, הני מילי היכא דקא עביד בידיים, Hani milei heicha
d'ka avid beyadayim, that's only if you directly took it. אבל גרמא
לא, Aval grama lo, if you indirectly caused it you would not
say that. תא שמע, Ta shema, אל שאול ואל בית הדמים אשר
המית את הגבעונים, El Shaul ve'el beit hadamim asher hemit et haGivonim,
that Shaul killed the גבעונים. Givonim. וכי היכן מצינו שהרג שאול את
הגבעונים? Vechi heichan matzinu sheharag Shaul et haGivonim? Where did we ever
find that Shaul killed the גבעונים? Givonim? אלא מתוך שהרג נוב עיר
כוהנים, Ella mitoch sheharag Nov ir kohanim, because he wiped out נוב
Nov the city of כוהנים, Kohanim, שהיו מספיקין להן מים ומזון, Shehayu
maspikin lahen mayim umazon, so he
so he destroyed the business of the גבעונים Givonim because the גבעונים
Givonim you know were put to work for the בית המקדש Beit
Hamikdash or you know for the מקדש, Mikdash, and they were working
for the כוהנים, Kohanim, so when he wiped out the city of
כוהנים, Kohanim, there goes the jobs of all the גבעונים Givonim that
were working for them. So in so מעלה עליו
הכתוב כאילו הרגן, Ma'aleh alav hakatuv ke'ilu haragan,
so it's like he killed the גבעונים Givonim as well. Okay, so
here you have some very heavy right rhetoric about the about how
terrible you know and exhortations which like again it's quite fascinating that
this is left to the very last דף. Yes.
And it's also interesting about like the way that the גנב Gannav
is treated throughout some of this. Like previously it was like really
that's okay, or really he gets off with that, and then to
end it with this to like... right,
right.
So I don't know you know I would say so that's I
think the question that we're supposed to be asking, the juxtaposition of
it's so terrible and then you have this תקנת השבים Takkanat Hashavim
and if he uses an object he doesn't have to pay for
it and if he makes the animal fatter he can ask for
the money difference and he can say הרי שלך לפניך. Harei shelcha
lefanecha. To some degree I think it's sort of this balance between
I don't know if I'd call it idealism but anyway idealism and
realism, like okay it's a terrible sin but you know you gotta
have certain but but in order to get people to give the
objects back and in order to actually address the real issues you
know it's sort of like not to get political but it's sort
of like you know people that sort of talk about law and
order and like let's lock them all up is not necessarily the
best way to address the problems of crime in society, right? So
I think that that's part of it, like yes it's a terrible
sin but... But that doesn't necessarily mean that the right way of
making society run more smoothly and more justly, you know, comes from,
you know, overly harsh reaction to this. I don't know. Now it
still seems to us it was a little bit too soft, the
rest of the מסכת masechet *masechet*, but I do think there's a
difference between how terrible the sin is and what the practical solution
is. Yes?
With respect,
there's a better example from last night.
Uh-oh, let's not get too political. Yes? Better example.
Listen, you didn't pay your tax, but that was the law. Use
the law.
Use the law.
That's the flip side of it. Right. Right. So meaning, it's not—right,
meaning, yeah, I think that that is the thing, that there seem
to be way too many loopholes, right? But I do think that
there is saying that there's a difference between, like, what the law
and what the sort of best societal response is and what the
whatever is. Okay. So now it says like this.
Don't do business with them anymore.
Okay. אבל לוקחין מן הנשים *Aval lokchin min hanashim*, you can buy
from women in different places things that's normal for them to sell.
What did it say in the משנה Mishna. *mishna* again?
Wool garments in Judea and linen garments in the Galilee and so
on. Okay, because you're not afraid that they're doing it without their
husband's permission. That's like a standard business for that women do in
those areas. תנו רבנן tanu rabanan. *Tanu Rabbanan*, again with the assumption
that all the property is their husband's. תנו רבנן Tano rabanan: לוקחין
מן הנשים כלי צמר ביהודה *Tanu Rabbanan lokchin min hanashim klei tzemer
b'Yehuda*, wool garments in Judea, וכלי פשתן בגליל *u'klei pishtan ba'Galil*, linen
in the Galilee. אבל לא יינות ושמנים וסלתות *Aval lo yeinot u'shmanim
v'saltot*, but do not buy from them, you know, wine and oil
and flour. I don't know, either you're—either you're afraid that they are—their
husbands have, you know, vineyard and they're doing it unjustly, or maybe
they're just trying to make some money. So the money they're supposed
to be using, the wine they're supposed to be using for the
house, they sell a little bit off to the side. So here's
the, you know, whatever, the reality's very different from ours where the
husband totally controlled all of the and owned, you know, all the
property. So those types of things you don't buy; that's not the
norm for them to have the right to be selling those things.
ולא מן העבדים *V'lo min ha'avadim*, and you can't buy from slaves,
ולא מן התינוקות *v'lo min hatinokot*, or not from children. אבל *Aval*—again,
all of these things are—you—the default assumption is they do not have
the right to be doing this. אבא שאול אומר *Abba Shaul omer*,
מוכרת אשה בארבע וחמשה דינרין *mocheret isha b'arba v'chamisha dinarin*, כדי לעשות
כיפה לראשה *k'dei la'asot kipa l'roshah*. Actually no, women are—ever hear the
idea of pin money, right? So women actually are allowed to sell
four and five—I don't know four and five what, but anyway, to
sell—does רש״י Rashi *Rashi* say four and five what? No. Anyway, so
I'm not sure if it's a number of objects or four and—anyway,
but you—she's allowed to sell a certain small number of things because
for pin money, you know, in order to buy a little hat
for her head. So yes, women do have a default permission from
their husbands
to, you know, sell, like, small little things. Again, I don't know
exactly what four and five is.
Five of the sheep?
I think so. What does the English say? Four and five what,
does it say?
Small things.
Four and five דינרים *dinars*.
Oh, דינרים *dinars*, I was wondering if it was a money value.
Okay. Oh, I'm sorry, it was right in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*!
I'm sorry. Okay. All right. Missed that word. Ha. ארבעה וחמישה דינרין
*arba'ah v'chamishah dinarin*. There you go. Who needs English? It's in the
גמרא *Gemara*. Okay. Anyway, four and five דינר *dinar* she can sell,
like, you know, and a four and five דינר *dinar* is not
a small amount. A דינר *dinar*'s a large amount. It's like—what is
it, $20, $100? I don't know what it is.
That's her expense, but it depends on whether it's a gold דינר
*dinar*.
Anyway, does that mean what does that mean? Every transaction can be
four and five דינר *dinar*? Four and five דינר *dinar* a month?
Like, I don't know how you're supposed to determine that. Anyway, moving
on.
But the שאלה *she'ila* is if it's—it's like when you go to
a check signed by a second person from your board or whatever.
If it's big enough. Right? But if it's under a certain amount,
we trust her that she's, like, within what she's— Ah,
so you just say every transaction within four and five דינר *dinar*?
Could be. Four and five דינר *dinar* is a significant amount—I mean,
not a trivial amount. Okay. וכולן שאמרו להטמין *V'chulan she'amru l'hatmin*, in
any of these cases, if they say, "keep it to yourself, keep
it quiet", אסור *assur*, forbidden. גבאי צדקה tzedakah. לוקחין מהם דבר מועט
אבל לא דבר מרובה *Gabbai tzedakah lokchin meihem davar muat aval lo
davar merubeh*. Now, if the question is who is getting from whom
in this line? Until now it means you can purchase from them.
So now it's saying you can buy from גבאי צדקה tzedakah. *gabbai
tzedakah* a little thing and not a lot?
No, the גבאי צדקה *gabbai tzedakah* can get from them.
I know, but I'm just saying you'll see the grammar won't work
in the rest of it, okay? But yes, I agree here that—that—the
sense of this line is גבאי צדקה *gabbai tzedakah* can purchase from
them, from women, like a little thing and not a lot.
Or like maybe they want to get—like they want to get צדקה
*tzedakah*. Do you assume this is stolen from the— Right, exactly.
So I'm sorry, so it's not purchase. You're right, you're right. I'm
sorry, I'm sorry. The גמרא *Gemara*—except, right, because that's going to come
up at the end. So the גבאי צדקה *gabbai tzedakah* can accept
small little donations, right? So they go knocking door to door and
the woman or the slave says, "Here's $5", the wife or the
slave, you don't say, "Wait, wait, let me—bring out your husband, let
me—make sure he's okay with it". So the same way there's a
presumption that they can, you know, certain things they're allowed to sell,
there's also a presumption that the master or the husband or whatever
will be the father will be okay with them giving a little
bit, a small amount of money or a little amount of their,
you know, of their food, whatever, to the גבאי צדקה *gabbai tzedakah*.
So גבאי צדקה *gabbai tzedakah* can take small donations from them. והבדדין
לוקחין מהן זיתים במידה ושמן במידה *V'habadadin lokchin meihen zeitim b'midah v'shemen
b'midah*.
So now the בדדין *badadin*... the wine pressers, you know, the people
that are the business of pressing, I'm sorry, of oil, other people's
oil, you can take large amounts of oil from them similar to
the discussion before about four and five סאה, because then you're not
afraid that they're stealing it. אבל לא זיתים במועט ושמן במועט, Aval
lo zeitim be-muat ve-shemen be-muat, but not a small amount of olives
and of oil, that you are afraid that they're stealing. רבן שמעון
בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel אומר לוקחין מן הנשים זיתים במועט,
omer lokhin min ha-nashim zeitim be-muat,
so I have the word במועט, bi-muat, you can take olives in
a small amount or on יום טוב Yontif time from women. בגליל
העליון, Ba-galil ha-elyon, in the Upper Galilee, שפעמים אדם בושה למכור על
פתח ביתו ונותן לאשתו ומוכרת, she-peamim adam bosh limkor al petach beito
ve-noten le-ishto u-mocheret, which is really lovely. A person is afraid to
sell such small amounts, like, it's announcing maybe that he doesn't have,
you know, how hard up he is that he has to sell
like even, you know, these small amounts. So because it is more
socially acceptable for women to sell small amounts as we've seen than
for men, men if they're having a business, why are you selling
these tiny little things, so sometimes he gets his wife to do
it for him. So even though this, so, so anyway, whatever those
circumstances are, since women will more often sell small amounts, even things
that we maybe did not list before were normally sold by women,
sometimes you can buy from women ונותן לאשתו ומוכרת. ve-noten le-ishto u-mocheret.
רבינא Ravina איקלע לבי מחוזא, ikla le-vei Mechuza, Ravina came to the
house of Mechuza. אתו נשי דבי מחוזא, Atu neshei de-vei Mechuza, the
women of Mechuza came out. רמו קמיה כבלי ושירותי, Remu kumei kavlei
ve-shirutei,
they threw to him like, you know, necklaces and bracelets, gold, you
know, golden objects to give to צדקה. He was there collecting צדקה.
קיבל מינייהו, Kibel mineihu, he accepted from them. אמר ליה רבה תוספאה
לרבינא, Amar lei Rabbah Tosfa’ah le-Ravina, so Rabbah Tosfa’ah said to Ravina,
והתניא גבאי צדקה מקבלין מהן דבר מועט אבל לא דבר מרובה? Ve-ha-tanya
gabbai tzedakah mekablin me-hen davar muat aval lo davar merubeh? You can
only accept from women small donations, not big donations. אמר ליה הני
מילי לנשי דמחוזא דבר מועט נינהו, Amar lei hanei mili le-neshei di-Mechuza
davar muat ninhu, the people of Mechuza are very wealthy, so for
them this counts as a small donation. Okay. That's
anyway, so that is taking things that you're afraid might be stolen.
All
right. משנה. mishna. And even, you know, things that are not like,
that we would not consider like technically stolen, you know, to us
of course, you know, the whole patriarchal sort of aspect to it
obviously is very difficult, but that was the reality of society. So,
you know, to put like the positive light, like, bypassing obviously the
whole patriarchal nature, but the point is even if you're like working,
even if you're a member of the household, you have, you can't
give something away if you don't have rights to it. You know,
and this is like an issue that comes up all the time
like we're dealing with a, you know, you're dealing in a store
with a, you know, the employee or whatever, you know, or somebody,
a waiter or whatever it is, and says "Don't, just don't worry
about it. It's on the house. Just take it." Or whatever, something
like that. Well, you're not the owner. Are you allowed, do you
have the right to tell me that it's on the house? You
know, so I mean those are real questions right that come up,
you know, so and employees helping themselves this is a little different,
you know, to, you know, to stuff that's in the, you know,
the, what do they call it? The supply closet, right? So the
idea here that even though you to a certain degree are part
of, you know, it's not out-and-out theft, but it still is גזילה
gezeilah if you don't have, if you don't have rights to that.
All right. You know, the whole issue about how people rationalize, they
actually did a study once where they put out like a bottle
of soda, an unmarked bottle of soda, like in, you know, in
the whatever in the employee lounge and like they saw like, you
know, people would like help themselves to it, right? You know, and
then they would put like a just a dollar on the table
and nobody would take it. So like the things we can rationalize
to ourselves, "Oh, it's just soda, I'm sure that anybody would be
okay with me," whatever, right? So either what? It's הפקר. hefker. It's
sitting there,
clearly it's meant to be taken. Right. Anyway, all right. So, next
משנה. Mishnah מוכין, Muchin, so that's how the גמרא ends. Okay, with
this real technical discussion of like what property if you're working for
somebody is it assumed that they're okay with you keeping, and which,
and you know, and what do you have to know technically belongs
to the owner and we can't assume they're okay with you keeping
it to yourself. Okay, to the point that it's so technical and
tiny, but to me it's very powerful in terms of what it
shows about how precise and careful you have to be. Okay. מוכין
שהכובס מוציא הרי אלו שלו. Muchin she-ha-koves motzi harei elu shelo. If
a, the launderer has, takes out some of the stuffing from a
pillow or whatever, some of it falls out in the process, it's
assumed he, that the owner doesn't care, he's allowed to keep it.
והסורק מוציא הרי אלו של בעל הבית. Ve-ha-sorek motzi harei elu shel
ba-al ha-bayit. But if the comber, I don't know, comber of flax
or I don't know exactly what these professions are, anyway if some
of the of the material comes out in the combing, he has
to return it to the owner, it's assumed that the owner wants
that back. כובס נוטל ג' חוטין והן שלו. Koves notel gimel chutin
ve-hen shelo. The, the
launderer can take three strings, they would sometimes put strings at the
bottom of a garment and he would like remove them, you know,
in the process, like maybe they would be strings that would like
sew the socks together or something. Anyway, so he takes out those
three strings and those are assumed that he can keep. יתר מכאן
הרי אלו של בעל הבית, Yoter mi-kan harei elu shel ba-al ha-bayit,
it goes to the
owner. אם היה שחור על גבי לבן נוטל את הכל והן שלו.
Im hayah shachor al gabi lavan notel et ha-kol ve-hen shelo. Clearly
they don't belong on the garment and he can take it all
and keep it. החייט ששייר את החוט כדי לתפור בו, Ha-chayat she-shiyer
et ha-chut kedei litpor bo, if a tailor left over a thread
enough to sew with. if a tailor leaves over a thread and
it's a long enough thread that you can actually use it to
sew, to do another stitch with, ומכניסו ג' על ג' umachniso gimmel
al gimmel or a little patch of clothing that is three by
three fingerbreadths, הרי אלו של בעל הבית harei elu shel baal habayit
it's assumed that the owner, if that's what's left over, again, this
is somebody that you've hired to do, you've presumably given them the
material, and then they have to give you this material back. It's
assumed that the owner still wants that. מה שהחרש מוציא, Ma shehecharash
motzi,
now how about a carpenter? So anything that falls off, again, you
gave him the lumber, and he's there and he's planing it or
whatever he's doing. So if something comes off במעצד, bematzad, which is
I think some type of a plane, הרי אלו שלו, harei elu
shelo, those are considered to be like small chips and the owner
doesn't care and he gets to keep it. ובכשיל, Uvakashil, things that
come up with a hatchet, those are bigger chips, הרי זה של
בעל הבית harei zeh shel baal habayit and it's considered that the
owner does want those wood chips and he has to give it
to the owner. ואם היה עושה אצל בעל הבית, Veim haya oseh
etzel baal habayit, but if he was working, he was sort of
brought into the owner's home and sent down to the owner's,
whatever, workroom in the basement, then אפילו הנסורת של בעל הבית, afilu
hinasoret shel baal habayit, even like
the sawdust belongs to the בעל הבית. baal habayit. If you're working
in the house, it's assumed that you leave everything for the owner.
If you're working in your house, some things are so trivial you
don't have to deliver back to the owner. תנו רבנן, Tano rabanan:
לוקחין מוכין מן הכובס, lokin mukhi min hakovess, מפני שהן שלו. mipnei
shehen shelo.
You can purchase from a launderer, you can purchase like some of
the stuffing material because as we read in the Mishnah, if it
falls out he's allowed to keep it. Okay, והכובס נוטל שני חוטין
העליונים והן שלו. Vehakovess notel shene chutin haelyonim vehen shelo. You can
also take two of the upper strings, upper threads, I don't know
the exact reality, but again, the way I imagine it, it's sort
of something like sometimes they sew your socks together when they launder
them so they don't whatever, so he removes those threads and he
keeps it. ולא יתן בו יותר משלושה חובין. Veloh yitten bo yoter
mishlosha chuvin.
This is some thing I didn't really fully understand. It's some type
of a way that he weaves in some thread so that when
you pull the garment, the garment can stretch, and it says that
he should not
put into the garment more than three of these, I really don't
understand what it's talking about. ולא יסרוק הבגד לשתיא אלא לערבו, Veloh
yisrok habeged leshishtia ela la'aravo,
when he is, now what's interesting is because now we're no longer
going on what are the small little things he's allowed to keep,
but we're actually talking to him, it's fascinating that this is here,
about how he has to do his job, the technical ways in
which you have to do the job to protect the property of
the person who you're doing. So we're giving him instructions on how
to launder clothing in a way that respects the property of the
person. Okay, so somehow by putting in more than three of these
stitches it might hurt the clothes, I don't know exactly what those
stitches are. And this is when you're combing the garment, don't comb
it, I forget which is the warp and which is the woof.
What does it say?
One of them is the warp and the other's woof. Anyway, one
of these is warp and one is woof. So when you're combing
the garment, comb it towards the שתי sheti but not towards the
ערב. arav. Right? Which is the woof? Warp. Warp. Okay, now
I don't know if that helps because I don't know what warp
is and I don't know what woof is. Anyway, fine. Comb it
like when they say when you cut meat, like cut against the
grain? Right? So when you comb, do you comb like in this
way or in that way? So comb with the שתי Sheti, and
not with the ערב. arav. Apparently the other way will damage the
garment. Okay. ומשויהו לאורכו ולא לרוחבו. Umashveihu le'orko veloh lerochbo.
If you have to what?
It's the warp. What? The vertical threads are the warp.
The vertical ones are the warp.
Right. What's vertical?
Okay, well, but okay. And שתי shati is the warp. So you
comb it vertically and not horizontally. Okay, I guess that means you're
stretching something more vertical. It seems that that's more going with the
grain than against the grain. What?
שתי, some, those are the threads that are like connected from the
top
and the bottom and the woof is something, right, that goes through
like that. Okay. So you go with the warp and not with
the woof. Now if you let's say have to trim a garment,
right, to get it even or whatever, I something like that, so
it says ומשויהו לאורכו ולא לרוחבו, umashveihu le'orko veloh lerochbo, trim it
at the length, not at the width, because you can always like
make the length a little, if you imagine something that's like, I
don't know, if you imagine a scarf, right,
so if you trim the edges, you trim the length, you have
a slightly shorter scarf but it's even. But if you trim the
width, it's like clearly that more compromises the integrity of the garment
if you're trimming the width than if you're trimming the length. Okay.
ואם היה להשוותו עד טפח רשאי, Veim haya lehashvoto ad tefach reshai,
and if you have to really like make it even, you can
even up to a טפח tefach trim off if it's necessary to
like even out the garment. So it's so funny. It's basically just
telling you how to do your job in a way that respects
the property of the owner, right? And you don't want to just
assume like that the market will take care of that, right? Like
this guy does a bad job, don't give your garments to him,
they do it in a way that ruins the garments or whatever.
Oh, when you trim off the טפח, tefach, right?
Who gets that piece? Well, that's an interesting question, but that's not
exactly what's
directly being addressed here.
What? No, it's not all about who gets it. Like which way
you comb the garment. Maybe you're right, maybe it's a little connected
because if I comb it one way it'll produce more threads that
I'll be able to keep. keep for myself. Maybe that's true. Anyway,
אמר מר amar mar שתי חוטין shetei chutin ואנא v'ana so anyway
he gets to keep two threads. ואנא ואנא v'ana v'ana שלוש shalosh
don't we say that up to three threads he gets to keep?
לא קשיא. lo kashya. הא דאלימי הא דקטיני. ha d'alimi ha d'katini.
Are they thick threads or thin threads? Thick, two. Thin, three. לא
יסרוק הבגד לשתי גב אל ארבעה. lo yisrok habeged l'shati gav el
arba'ah. Do not comb it to the with the warp, the length,
but rather the woof, the weft. Okay. והתניא איפכא? v'hatanya ipcha? Don't
we have a braisa that says the opposite? Go the weft, the
woof and not the warp? לא קשיא הא בגלימא הא בסרבלא. lo
kashya ha b'glima ha b'sarvla. Is it a cloak or is it
a coat? What difference does it make? So Rashi basically says that
a... let me remind myself what Rashi says. Rashi says a סרבלא
sarvla is a like is a... made more for the appearances. So
when you do it for the שתי way, the... now I'm confused...
the warp way... anyway, in short, one way it looks nicer, the
other way it lasts longer. Okay. So it's like you know when
I go to the dry cleaner they have this sign up that
says something like, you know, I don't know, get your clothes dry
cleaned regularly, but I think if like you read the literature, like
if you over dry clean your clothes it's not good for them
in terms of them lasting long. So some things make it look...
one way makes it look nicer, the other thing makes it look...
makes it last longer, and so something that's basically for looking nice,
you do it in the way that makes it look nicer. The
thing that's there more for, you know, just keeping you warm, you
do it in a way that makes it last longer. Okay. So
now the Gemara says like this: ולא יתפור בו יותר משלוש חובים.
v'lo yitpor bo yoter m'shalosh chovin. Don't put more of these three
stitches in it that are made for stretching it. בעי רבי ירמיה
אמתויי ואתויי חד? ba'ei Rabi Yirmiah amtuyei v'atuyei chad? When... what counts
as a stitch? You know, up and down is one stitch? או
דלמא אמתויי ואתויי תרי? o dilma amtuyei v'atuyei terei? Going in one
way and coming back out the other way counts as two? So
you know, take... all right, we don't know. משויהו לאורכו ולא לרוחבו.
mashveihu l'orko v'lo l'rochvo. You trim it lengthwise but not widthwise. והתניא
איפכא? v'hatanya ipcha? Braisa says the opposite. לא קשיא הא בגלימא הא
בהמייני. lo kashya ha b'glima ha b'hamyanei. One is a cloak and
the other is a המייני, hamyanei, which Rashi says is... that basically
you see more the edge... the lengthwise edges, you don't see the
widthwise edges. So trimming it, I don't exactly know what it is.
What does it say it is? Like a belt? I think it's
a belt, right? So if it's a belt, somehow Rashi says that
trimming the width is not as apparent as trimming the length. It
says because I mean then the host says the
length is not visible when it's worn. Right, when it's visible you
don't see the length, so
it's more important to have a good looking width than it is...
the length could be a little bit uneven because it overlaps I
guess when you tie it around yourself. Okay. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan.
אין לוקחין מן הסורק מוכין מפני שאינו שלו. ein lokchin min hasorek
mochin mipnei she'eino shelo. When it comes to a comber, as opposed
to a launderer, you cannot buy the stuffing because he's not entitled
to that. ובמקום שנהגו להיות שלו לוקחין. uv'makom she'nahagu lihyot shelo lokchin.
But in places where the custom in the community is that he
gets to keep it, then you can purchase it from him. ובכל
מקום לוקחין מהן כר מלא מוכין וכסת מלאה מוכין. uv'chol makom lokchin
mehen kar malei mochin v'cheset maleia mochin. In any places you can
buy from people pillows filled with stuffing. מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? קנינהו
בשינוי. kaninhu b'shinui. Even if he stole the stuffing, now it's a
שינוי. shinui. So again, here we just have like, you know, completely...
aren't you helping him provide a market? Maybe again, you don't have
to suspect it. Maybe it's even if he stole it, it was
a שינוי. shinui. But again, it gets back to those interesting questions
of providing a market. תנו רבנן. אין לוקחין מגרדי לא אירין ולא
נירין. ein lokchin migardi lo irin v'lo nirin. You do not buy
from a weaver neither אירין irin and נירין, nirin, which is... oh
Rashi... it's basically like the warp and the woof that's like around
the shuttle. Is that what it's called, the shuttle? Or whatever, the
spindle? Okay. So again, because all of that if there's any leftover
thread, it all goes to the owner. ולא פונקלין ולא שיורי פקיעות.
v'lo punkalin v'lo shiyurei pekiyot. And all of these are different types
of things that are, I don't know, how do they translate it?
Different types of things that are left on the loom or something.
What did they say there? פונקלין, punkalin, they say tapestry bobbins. Bobbins,
yeah, I looked it up in the English too. Bobbins, that helped
me a lot. Okay. I thought... I thought bobbins was from the
Hobbit. Isn't his name Bilbo Baggins?
Oh, that's Baggins, so that's where the thread comes from. That's where
the thread comes from.
Okay. Anyway, you don't buy these different types of things which are
part of the threading of which they're the, you know, the threads
that are used or the implements because those are all belong to
the owner. אבל לוקחין מהן בגד מנומר,
aval
lokchin
mehen beged menumar, but what you can buy is a garment that
is made out of a patchwork garment. Even though reasonably you could
say, where did he get all those patches? Hmm, I wonder. Okay,
nevertheless, okay, because of this idea of... he's קנהו בשינוי. konehu b'shinui.
Even if he stole those patches, and hopefully he didn't, but he's
קנהו בשינוי. konehu b'shinui. ערב ושתי טווי ואריג נמי erev v'shati tavui
v'arig nami also buy from them warp and woof if it is
spun or woven because again, even though he's not supposed to keep
the warp and woof, if he did keep it, if he did
steal it, at least he's קנהו בשינוי konehu b'shinui because he has
now spun and woven it. השתא hashta now the Gemara says: השתא
טווי שקיל אריג מיבעיא? hashta tavui shakil arig mibaya? If you can
take it once it's spun, of course once it's woven? The weaving
comes after. So of course it’s more of a שינוי. shinui. הגמרא
Gemara says no, מאי ארי? mai ari? טיכי. tichi. No, woven would
mean here not woven after spinning, but a type of a twisted,
twisted string, so with... it’s not spun, but it’s twisted instead. But
either of those is a שינוי. shinui. תנו רבנן: אין לוקחין מן
הצבע, ein lokchin min hatzaya, you do not buy from a dyer,
לא אותות ולא דוגמאות, lo otot velo dugmaot, neither samples or tests
or samples. רש״י Rashi says that an אות ot is basically you
bring him a little bit of clothing and you say here, practice
the dye on this piece of the garment before you do it
on the whole garment, and a דוגמא, dugma, an example, is you
actually say here’s an example of the color I want the garment
to look like in the end. Okay, so these are little things
that the owner would give to the dyer so he would be
able to test or know what the owner wanted. And obviously now
if the dyer is selling these little samples, you can’t buy them
from him because we presume the owner wants them back. Okay,
so it’s quite fascinating, even these tiny little things we assume the
owner wants them back. ולא תלושים של צמר, Velo tluishim shel tzemer,
and not sort of plucked-off wool from presumably garments that he was
working with, because, you know, in the process of dyeing, some wool
comes off, we assume the owner wants it back. אבל לוקחין מהן
בגד צבוע, Aval lokchin mehen beged tzavua, but if you can buy
an actual dyed garment, because maybe, you know, who knows, maybe the
owner said forget it, you ruined it, keep it, or whatever, you
know, and even if he did steal it, he was קנה koneh
with a שינוי. shinui. It would be interesting that צבע tzeva is
a שינוי. shinui. You know, what is that? A שינוי השם? shinui
hashem? Is that really a שינוי? shinui? Anyway, טווי ובגדים, tavui ubgadim,
טווי ובגדים, tavui ubgadim, and spun wool and clothes, because all of
those things, if he got the raw wool, we assume by spinning
it and making it into clothes, he was קנה koneh it. השתא
טווי שקיל, Hashta tavui shakil, if just spinning the wool he can
buy it because he’s קנה koneh with a שינוי, shinui, בגדים מיבעיא,
begadim mibaya, so certainly once it’s already a garment. So the הגמרא
Gemara says, מאי בגדים? mai begadim? נמטי. namti. No, clothes mean not
a whole woven garment, it means like a piece of felt. So
that was not spun, it was a pressed piece of wool; also
that you can buy from him. Again, the presumption the גוזל gozel
ate, he ate it, so he paid for it, I know, I
know. Right. תנו רבנן: הנותן עור לעבדן, hanoten or la'avdan, הקיצועין והתלושין,
hakitzuin vehatlushin, הרי אלו שלו. harei elu shelo. You give leather to
the tanner to turn into... you give skin to the tanner to
turn into leather. Okay, so the cut-off, the trimmed pieces of the
piece of the skin and the sort of hair that comes off
in the process of working the skin, הרי אלו של בעל הבית.
harei elu shel baal habayit. I think I misread that. Anyways, that
goes to the owner. You assume the owner wants the trimmed pieces
of leather. והעולה ומשתטף במים, Veha'ola umishatef bamayim, but the stuff that
comes off when you’re submerging it in water, whatever pieces come to
the top of the water, הרי אלו שלו, harei elu shelo, you
get to keep that. Again, all this stuff seems so tiny and
trivial, but to me it’s very beautiful, you know, that, a, the
מסכת ends with finally some exhortations about how bad it is to
steal, and, b, this tiny sense of like every little penny you
have to be exacting about. Do I have a right to keep
this little stuff that was left over? It’s not mine. Like, you
know, so that gets back to the point that even if you
steal a פרוטה, pruta, it’s like you steal the life, you have
to really care about every little פרוטה. pruta. I find it very
powerful. Okay. אם היה שחור, Im haya shachor, if it was black
thread on white, then even if it’s multiple threads, the launderer can
keep it. אמר רב יהודה: Amar Rav Yehuda: קיצרא שמיה, kitsra shmei,
the name of a launderer in Aramaic is קיצרא, kitsra, וקיצרא שקיל,
vekitsra shakil, and he can take the stuff at the edge of
the garment, the strings at the edge of the garment. Okay, or
what רש״י Rashi: says what he trims off the garment, אבא שקלי.
ava shaklei. אמר רב יהודה: Amar Rav Yehuda: הכל עולים למנין תכלת,
hakol olim leminyan tchelet, those extra threads that are added at the
bottom of the garment, even though they’re normally taken off by the
launderer, if you don’t take them off, then they count towards תכלת,
tchelet, meaning ציצית. tzitzit. What does that mean? It means you put
your ציצית, tzitzit, you have to put them not at the very
edge of the garment, but like a little bit inset into the
garment. Okay, so where do you measure the edge of the garment
from which you have to go inset the ציצית? tzitzit? So here
it says you measure it, if those three strings are on, you
measure it from those strings. You don’t have to pretend like the
strings aren’t there and go more into the garment. Okay, which you
could have easily said opposite. You could have said if those threads
are meant to be removed, then... You’re not understanding, Jen? Yeah, I
don't know how you knew that, that's what I would have thought
it meant, then you do have to start from where those are.
Look at רש״י: Rashi הכל עולים למנין תכלת, Hakol olim leminyan tchelet,
רש״י says: אותן שלושה חוטין אם לא קצרן הכובס, otan shelosha chutin
im lo ktzaran hakoves, eight lines down in the left-hand side or
from the narrow lines, אותן שלושה חוטין אם לא קצרן הכובס, otan
shelosha chutin im lo ktzaran hakoves, עולים למידת מלא קשר גודל, olim
lemiddat melo kesher godel, שצריך להרחיק התכלת, she'tzarich leharchik hatchelet, you have
to keep the... you have to put the תכלת, tchelet, meaning ציצית,
tzitzit, you have to put it, meaning a size of a thumb-width
away from the edge of the garment, משפת הבגד misfat habeged (מסכת
מנחות). Masechet Menachot Right? So if like if you look at a
normal ציצית, tzitzit, right, the strings are coming down from this, right?
Have you ever seen like, right? Right? So it has to be
this width from the edge of the garment. So where do you
start counting the edge? So if these three strings are still here,
you count the edge from the, they're included in the garment. Even
you don't pretend as if well they're made to be removed, they're
not part of the garment. If you're not removing them, they are
part of the garment. That's right. So it just, it's not a
centimeter. Yeah, you don't, you don't have to move it in, you
can move it in from this point and not from that point.
Right. So it's just a technical point of where do you start
your ציצית Tzitzis string from. Okay? The יצחק בריק Yitzchak Brick capitalized,
but יצחק Yitzchak my son is מקפיד, makpid, he doesn't like counting
the garment starting there, he only counts the garment starting after the
three strings. החייט ששייר את החוט, Hachayat sheshiyer et hachut, if the,
if the tailor leaves over a thread that's enough as the size
of a needle or whatever, no, enough to, to thread with it,
to make a stitch, then it goes to the owner. Then it's
enough of, significant enough that it goes back to the owner. Again,
the owner provided the thread. Okay. וכמה לתפור, V'kamah litpor, how much
is enough thread to stitch with? אמר רב אסי מלא מחט וחוץ
למחט. Amar Rav Assi mlei machat v'chutz l'machat. מלא מחט וחוץ למחט,
Mlei machat v'chutz l'machat, the length of the needle outside of the
needle. So what does that mean? איבעיא להו, what does that mean?
מלא מחט וחוץ למחט כמלא מחט, Mlei machat v'chutz l'machat k'mlei machat,
does it mean the length of the needle plus outside of the
needle another needle's length, so essentially it's two needles' length? או דילמא
מלא מחט וחוץ למחט משהו, O dilma mlei machat v'chutz l'machat mash'hu,
or the length of the needle plus only a little bit more,
like, you know, to go out through the hole of the needle?
תא שמע, דתניא, החייט ששייר את החוט פחות מכדי לתפור בו, Hachayat
sheshiyer et hachut pachos mikdei litpor bo, if the, if the tailor
leaves over a string not enough to stitch with, ומטלית שפחותה משלוש
על שלוש, umatlis shepachusa mishalosh al shalosh, or a little patch less
than three by three finger widths, בזמן שבעל הבית מקפיד עליהן הרי
אלו של בעל הבית, bizman sheba'al habayis makpid aleihen harei elu shel
ba'al habayis, so nor, so meaning the owner's still entitled to get
them if he wants to. The default in these cases when it's
that small is that the tailor keeps it, but that doesn't mean
the owner isn't entitled to ask for it back if he wants
to. So if the owner is מקפיד, makpid, you give it to
the owner. אין בעל הבית מקפיד, Ein ba'al habayis makpid, if he's
not מקפיד, makpid, which is the presumption in this case, הרי אלו
שלו, harei elu shelo, he gets to keep it. So אי אמרת
בשלמא מלא מחט וחוץ למחט כמלא מחט, ei amart bishlama mlei machat
v'chutz l'machat k'mlei machat, so if you say that the amount that
goes to the owner is when it's a double needle length, so
פחות מכאן הרי חזי לסיכסא, pachos mikan harei chazi l'sichsa, so we
understand why you have to say less than that goes to the
tailor because less than that is at least somewhat usable. You can
use it to make like a סיכסא, sichsa, what is a סיכסא
sichsa again here? Oh, one of those stitches that we discussed earlier
that you make in these garments. אלא אי אמרת מלא מחט וחוץ
למחט משהו הוא, Ela ei amart mlei machat v'chutz l'machat mash'hu hu,
so but if the only thing that the owner gets, I mean
if the owner gets, excuse me, up to the point that it's
even just a needle length plus a little bit more, so פחות
מכאן, pachos mikan, so if less than that goes to the tailor,
less than that what do you use a tiny little piece of
thread a half a centimeter wide for, you know, למאי חזי, l'mai
chazi, why are we even saying it goes to the tailor, nobody
has any use for it? אלא שמע מינה מלא מחט וחוץ למחט
כמלא מחט. Ela shema mina mlei machat v'chutz l'machat k'mlei machat. It
must be we're talking about something a little bit bigger, so less
than that is at least, could be, it's meaningful to say it
belongs to the tailor, there's some way to use something smaller than
that. שמע מינה, Shema mina, that makes sense. Alright. מה שחרש, Ma
shecharash, what the carpenter sort of comes off from the planing, that
goes to the carpenter, and what comes off from the, you know,
the hatcheting, that goes to the owner. So רמינהי, remini, I'll ask
on this. מה שחרש מוציא במעצד, Ma shecharash motzi b'ma'atzad, what he,
what comes off through I think in this means a plane, והנפסל
במגירה, vehanifsal b'mageirah, and stuff that comes off with the saw, הרי
אלו של בעל הבית, harei elu shel ba'al habayis, it goes to
the owner. So our משנה Mishnah said the מעצד ma'atzad goes to
the carpenter, and this ברייתא Braisa says that the plane, the stuff
that comes off with the plane goes to the owner. Okay, and
the end of the ברייתא Braisa is והיוצא מתחת מקדח vehayotze mitachas
makdeiach or מקדח, makdeiach, how do you pronounce this? What? מקדח. Makdeiach.
Okay, which is an awl, right you know like a pointy thing
that you make a hole in, so that's tiny little shavings that
don't do anybody any good, okay, ומתחת רהיטני, umitachas rahitni, and from
a רהיטני rahitni which is I have no, no idea what that
is. A plane they say. That's a plane. והנגרר במגירה, Vehanigrar b'mageirah,
or something that came with a saw but not because you're sawing
it like, you know, you know like down, you're sort of shaving
it with a saw. So those smaller things הרי שלו, harei shelo,
the carpenter gets to keep them. So anyway, we got the problem.
In our משנה Mishnah, it says a מגירה mageirah the carpenter keeps,
here it says the מגירה mageirah the owner keeps. So אמר רבא
באתרא דתנא דידן, Amar Rava b'asra detanna didan, in the place of
our תנא Tanna of our משנה, Mishnah איכא תרתי חציני. ika tarti
chatzini. There are two types of חציני chatzini as a מגירה. mageirah.
Okay. לרבתי קרו לה כשיל. L'rabasi karu lei kashil. So, I mean,
excuse me, not מגירה, mageirah, מעצד. ma'atzad. Okay. So the, the big
one they call a כשיל, kashil, ולזוטרתי קרו לה מעצד. ul'zutrasi karu
lei ma'atzad. They call it a מעצד. ma'atzad. So that's why our
משנה Mishna said the stuff from the מעצד ma'atzad goes to the
carpenter and from the כשיל kashil goes to the owner. Because that
basically means the small and the big version of this מעצד. ma'atzad.
Okay. באתרא דתנא ברא, B'asra detanna bara, in the place of the
other תנא, Tanna, the ברייתא we quoted, חדא היא, chada hi, there's
only one, they only have one of these מעצדs ma'atzad and it's
the big one, וקרו לה מעצד, v'karu lei ma'atzad, and they call
it a מעצד ma'atzad and therefore since it's that, so they say
the מעצד ma'atzad goes to the owner because they're talking about the
big version. Our משנה says the מעצד maatzad goes to the carpenter,
because when you have two types, the מעצד maatzad you use for
the small version and that goes to carpenter and the bigger version
is what goes to the owner. Fine. אי הוה עביד אצל בעל
הבית, ee hava avid etzel baal habayis, but if the guy was
working in the owner's, you know, workspace, then everything gets left to
the owner. Okay, תנו רבנן. מסטתי אבנים, mesatetei avanim, people that, you
know, carve stones, there's no... taking the remnants of the pebbles, that's
not considered stealing because again, that's what, I guess you'd assume any
of the stuff that comes off from the carving of the stones
the owner doesn't want. מפסקי אילנו מפסקי גפנים, mepaskei ilano mepaskei gefanim,
people that, like, prune trees and prune vines, מנכשי היגי menachshei higi
or that they cut down, you know, cut thornbushes, מנכשי זרעים menachshei
zeraim or they weed, for, you know, in gardens, ועודרי ירקות v'odrei
yerakot and or they remove, you know, vegetables, extra, extra like crowded
vegetables, so in all these cases, do they get to get the
stuff that they're pulling out of the ground? בזמן שבעל הבית מקפיד
עליהם, bizman shebaal habayis makpid aleihem, if the owner wants them, יש
בהם משום גזל, yesh bahem mishum gezel, then it is a problem.
אין בעל הבית מקפיד עליהם, ein baal habayis makpid aleihem, if he
doesn't care, הרי אלו שלו. harei elu shelo. Of course, it would
be nice if it told you what the default was. Okay, until
now we've been saying what the default is. This doesn't really help.
Maybe it means there's no default. You have to clarify in each
case. אמר רב יהודה. Amar Rav Yehuda. כשות וחזיז kashus v'chaziz אין
בו משום גזל, ein bo mishum gezel, ובאתרא דקפדי, uv'atra d'kapdi, יש
בו משום גזל. yesh bo mishum gezel. כשות kashus and חזיז chaziz
which are different types of things that are grow with the grain,
okay, and you know, so if you basically like, I don't know,
how did they explain what כשות kashus and חזיז chaziz is? Hops
and green grain. So things sometimes these are cut down and then
they regrow. And the classic thing would be to cut them and
to have the grain grow again, you're sure
about כשות. kashus. Okay, anyway, so you're working for the owner, again,
is the assumption that you get to keep this or not? So
he says the default
is that you do get to keep them, but if the owner
says he wants them, then it is a problem. אמר רבינא. Amar
Ravina. ומטא מחסיא אתרא דקפדי הוא. u'mata Mechasya atra d'kapdi hu. And
ומטא מחסיא Mata Mechasya is a place where we assume that people
are מקפיד makpid and therefore it is a גזל gezel problem. Again,
ending on a very mundane note, but I actually think it's a
very beautiful note, you know? It's basically, it ends with telling you
whether you're allowed to keep paper clips, you know, from your supply
closet, right? I mean, and that's the stuff that we all need
work on is that type of care in the tiny little issues.
הדרן עלך הגוזל בתרא וסליקא לה מסכת
בבא קמא.
Hadran alach HaGozeil Batra u'selika lah Masechet Bava
Kamma.